Guide to the David B. McCall Papers, 1939-1999 and undated, bulk 1980-1994
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
David B. McCall papers 1939-1999 and undated bulk 1980-1994
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
McCall, David B.
21.8 linear feet Extent: 12,600 Items
David B. McCall was an advertising executive and humanitarian. He was the originator of the idea for the children's educational television series Schoolhouse Rock. The David B. McCall Papers span the years 1939-1999, with the bulk documenting the years 1980-1994, and are comprised of clippings, correspondence, business reports, photographs, scrapbooks, speeches and writings, videocassettes, audio tapes and phonograph records. In particular, three main areas of McCall's career are represented: as an advertising executive and partner in agencies such as Young & Rubicam, Ogilvy Benson & Mather, McCaffrey & McCall, David J. Mahoney, Inc., the Sawyer Miller Group, and Shepardson Stern and Kaminsky; as a corporate director for the Hunter Fan Company, Save the Children, and two local radio broadcasting corporations, among others; and as a humanitarian involved with organizations such as the Committee for the Support of Roe v. Wade, CARE, and Refugees International. In addition, there is a substantial body of McCall's speeches and writings that reflect both the wide range of his professional and personal interests and commitments as well as his status as a public intellectual in high demand, as well as a number of files containing correspondence, clippings and articles concerning David Ogilvy, McCall's mentor in advertising. Major advertising campaigns represented in this collection include Mercedes Benz of North America, North American Philips, Life magazine, the American Can Company, Lever Brothers Company, and the Zippo Manufacturing Company, along with public relations work for such clients as the National Football League, Puerto Rico Telephone Company (PRTC), and the Regional Bell Operating Companies. Major humanitarian issues documented in the collection include the Unsell protest movement against the war in Vietnam, tobacco advertising aimed at children, land mine removal, refugee welfare, and support of abortion rights. McCall was also involved in political campaigns for a number of notable candidates, such as John Lindsay (New York), Harvey Gannt (North Carolina), George Kevarian (Massachusetts), Ramón Mitra (Philippines) and Mario Vargas Llosa (Peru). While McCall is recognized as the originator of the idea behind the popular children's educational television series Schoolhouse Rock!, the collection contains very little documentation concerning that project apart from a copy of the original soundtrack.
RL.00862
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Some use copies are available in the collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The David B. McCall Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2003.
Biographical Note
1928 Mar. 13 Born in New York City
1940-1941 Attended Indian Mountain School (Lakeville Conn.); member of Editorial Board of the school publication, The Scop (sic)
1942-1945 Attended The Hotchkiss School (Lakeville, Conn.)
1945-1946 Attended The Collegiate School (New York, N.Y.)
1946-1947 Stationed with the U.S. Army of Occupation, Japan. Attained rank of Private First Class
1948 Entered Yale University. Dropped out after one year
1950 Began work at Young & Rubicam advertising agency, first in the mail room and later as a copy writer
1951 Joined Ogilvy, Benson & Mather (OBM) advertising agency. Advanced to become chief copy writer
1953 Joined the David J. Mahoney, Inc. agency as chief copy writer
1955 Rejoined Ogilvy, Benson & Mather
1960 Became copy chief at Ogilvy, Benson & Mather
1960 Promoted to Senior Vice President and Director at Ogilvy, Benson & Mather
1962 Left Ogilvy, Benson & Mather, along with fellow OBM executive James McCaffrey, to take over the C.J. LaRoche & Co. agency. C.J. LaRoche renamed LaRoche, McCaffrey & McCall
1964 Part-time speech writer for John Lindsay (then Mayor of New York)
1967 Chester LaRoche retired from LaRoche, McCaffrey & McCall. The company continued to include him in its name until 1972.
1969 LaRoche, McCaffrey & McCall became a publicly-traded company
1971 Worked on a campaign to unsell the U.S. war in Vietnam
1972 LaRoche, McCaffrey & McCall renamed McCaffrey & McCall
1973 Developed the idea for Schoolhouse Rock!, an award-winning children's television series that used music to teach math and other skills
1973-1988 Chairman, C.E.O. and Creative Director, McCaffrey & McCall, Inc.
1988 Retired from McCaffrey & McCall; named Chairman Emeritus
1989-1993 Partner, Sawyer Miller Group, a communications and public relations firm
1992 Joined Refugees International as an aid worker and contributor
1993 Left Sawyer Miller Group; named Chairman of public relations firm Shepardson Stern & Kaminsky
1999 Apr. 18 Died in an automobile accident during an aid mission in Albania
Collection Overview
The David B. McCall Papers span the years 1939-1999, with the bulk documenting the years 1980-1994, and are comprised of clippings, correspondence, business reports, photographs, scrapbooks, speeches and writings, videocassettes, audio tapes and phonograph records. In particular, three main areas of McCall's career are represented: as an advertising executive and partner in agencies such as Young & Rubicam, Ogilvy Benson & Mather, McCaffrey & McCall, David J. Mahoney, Inc., the Sawyer Miller Group, and Shepardson Stern and Kaminsky; as a corporate director for the Hunter Fan Company, Save the Children, and two local radio broadcasting corporations, among others; and as a humanitarian involved with organizations such as the Committee for the Support of Roe v. Wade, CARE, and Refugees International. In addition, there is a substantial body of McCall's speeches and writings that reflect both the wide range of his professional and personal interests and commitments as well as his status as a public intellectual in high demand, as well as a number of files containing correspondence, clippings and articles concerning David Ogilvy, McCall's mentor in advertising. Major advertising campaigns represented in this collection include Mercedes Benz of North America, North American Philips, Life magazine, the American Can Company, Lever Brothers Company, and the Zippo Manufacturing Company, along with public relations work for such clients as the National Football League, Puerto Rico Telephone Company (PRTC), and the Regional Bell Operating Companies. Major humanitarian issues documented in the collection include the Unsell protest movement against the war in Vietnam, tobacco advertising aimed at children, land mine removal, refugee welfare, and support of abortion rights. McCall was also involved in political campaigns for a number of notable candidates, such as John Lindsay (New York), Harvey Gannt (North Carolina), George Kevarian (Massachusetts), Ramón Mitra (Philippines) and Mario Vargas Llosa (Peru). While McCall is recognized as the originator of the idea behind the popular children's educational television series Schoolhouse Rock!, the collection contains very little documentation concerning that project apart from a copy of the original soundtrack.
The collection is organized into 12 series that broadly outline the sequence of McCall's business and humanitarian activities: the Biographical and Personal Materials Series, the Ogilvy & Mather Series, the McCaffrey & McCall Series, the Radio Stations Series, the Sawyer Miller Group Series, the Hunter Fan Company Series, the Shepardson, Stern & Kaminsky Series, the Refugees International Series, the Speeches Series, the Writings Series, and the Portfolio Series. In addition, non-print materials have been removed to the Audiovisual Materials Series. Large-format print materials have been removed from their original series locations and relocated to Oversize Materials locations; these items have been cross-referenced to the points in the body of the collection from which they were removed.
The Biographical and Personal Materials Series contains materials relating to McCall's childhood and family life, and includes correspondence, photographs, biographical sketches, resumes and obituary notices. The Ogilvy & Mather Series includes correspondence and articles pertaining to the agency, along with profiles and tributes to agency founder David Ogilvy and correspondence between Ogilvy and McCall. The McCaffrey & McCall Series includes correspondence, corporate publications and client files. Legal documents that detail McCall's initial investment and employment in the C.J. Laroche & Co. agency, which was eventually renamed McCaffrey & McCall, are included. Major clients include Mercedes-Benz of North America, the New York Zoological Society, and Save the Children. The agency was also involved in the political campaign of New York Mayor John Lindsay. The Radio Stations Series includes correspondence, periodic reports and profit-and-loss statements for the 790 Communications Corporation and the 1340 Broadcasting Corporation, radio broadcasting corporations in which McCaffrey & McCall had invested, and in which McCall remained involved after retiring from the agency. The Sawyer Miller Group Series contains administrative records, correspondence and client files. Sawyer Miller was instrumental in helping the telecommunications industry after the breakup of the Bell system into regional operating companies. Other clients included the National Football League and the Puerto Rico Telephone Company, along with a number of political candidates.
The Hunter Fan Company Series consists primarily of reports pertaining to periodic meetings of the Board of Directors in addition to some information on marketing strategies and advertising campaigns. The Shepardson, Stern & Kaminsky Series contains administrative files and correspondence relating to internal operations and political advertising, as well as files documenting McCall's advocacy work on a tobacco-free initiative aimed at children. The Refugees International Series documents McCall's involvement in a number of humanitarian efforts undertaken by Refugees International, including relief for refugee children and land mine eradication. The series includes correspondence, travel itineraries and trip journals kept by McCall, as well as printed materials from Refugees International and other humanitarian organizations. The Speeches Series includes texts of speeches, talks, and commencement addresses given by McCall, along with a small collection of speeches given by others. There is also a set of speech files that contain clippings, writing fragments, and other materials used to compose or plan speeches. In a few cases, speeches are accompanied by supporting materials and relevant correspondence. The Writings Series includes letters to the editors of various publications, journal articles, poetry and other writings by McCall, along with a small collection of writings by others. The Portfolio Series contains clippings, copies of advertisements and scrapbook contents relating primarily to McCall's early career. The Audiovisual Materials Series includes documentary and promotional films, commercials and radio spot announcements, especially concerning the Roe v. Wade court case and demining efforts supported by Refugees International. Oversize materials have been moved to the Oversize Materials Series.
Other materials relating to this collection may be found in the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives: Competitive Advertisements Collection; the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives: Corporation Vertical Files, the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives: Advertising Vertical Files, and the Arthur Einstein Papers. Materials relating particularly to Ogilvy & Mather may also be found in the John E. Brennan Papers, the Kensinger Jones Papers, the Robert S. Smith Papers, and the Edgar Hatcher Papers. Additionally, materials relating to Save the Children may be found in the collection African-Americans in Film: Collection of Press Books, Campaign Books, Advertising Manuals, Etc., the Africa News Service (Durham, N.C.) Leroy T. Walker Africa News Service Archives, the J.B. Matthews Papers, the Amber Arthun Warburton Papers, and the North Carolina Council of Churches Records.
Subject Headings
McCall, David B.; Gannt, Harvey; Kevarian, George; Lindsay, John V. (John Vliet); Mitra, Ramón V., 1928?-; Ogilvy, David, 1911-; Vargas Llosa, Mario, 1936-; Life (New York, N.Y.); American Can Company; Care (Firm); Save the Children (U.S.); Lever Brothers Company; Mercedes-Benz of North America; National Football League; North American Philips Co; Ogilvy, Benson & Mather; Puerto Rico Telephone Company; Refugees International (Organization); Young & Rubicam; Zippo Manufacturing Company; Advertising executives; Advertising executives -- United States; Advertising -- History; Advertising agencies; Advertising agencies -- United States; Humanitarian assistance; Regional Bell Operating Companies; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975 -- Protest movements -- United States; Advertising and children -- United States; Advertising -- Tobacco -- United States; Pro-choice movement; Land mines; Humanitarian assistance, American -- Foreign countries; Non-governmental organizations; Television advertising; Radio advertising; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Clippings; Scrapbooks; Videocassettes; Speeches; Photographs; Sound recordings; Documentary films
Contents of Collection
- Biographical and Personal Materials Series, 1940-1999 and undated, (1 box)
  Contains materials relating to McCall's childhood and family life, and includes correspondence, photographs, biographical sketches, resumes and obituary notices. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Biographical sketches, undated (Box 1)
  - Birthday greeting, To David at 70, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Charitable donations, 1980-1986 (Box 1)
  - Childhood, The Scop (sic), Indian Mountain School (Lakeville, Conn.) publication, 1940-1941 (Box 1)
    As a student, McCall sat on the editorial board of this school publication.
  - Correspondence
    - Group for the South Fork,, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Bradley, Bill, Sen. (D-N.J.), 1988, 1993 (Box 1)
    - McCall, Susan, condolence letters, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
      Susan McCall, David's wife, also worked in advertising.
    - Stilwell, Gen. Joseph W., correspondence on a film project, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Genealogy inquiries, ca. 1980 (Box 1)
  - Obituary notices, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Personal horoscope, undated (Box 1)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1)
  - Resumes; and Curriculum Vitae, 1988 and undated (Box 1)
  - Travel
    - Ecuador, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Trip itineraries, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
- Ogilvy & Mather Series (Includes Ogilvy, Benson & Mather), 1958-1992 and undated, (1 box)
  Contains correspondence and articles pertaining to McCall's tenure at the agency, 1951-1953 and 1955-1962, including profiles and tributes to agency founder David Ogilvy and correspondence between Ogilvy and McCall. Other materials pertaining to McCall's work at Ogilvy, Benson & Mather may be found in the Portfolio Series and Oversize Materials. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Articles about Ogilvy & Mather (Box 1)
    - Further Confessions of an Adman, by Eleanor Berman, Success, 1984 Feb. (Box 1)
    - God, He Was Fun to Work For, by David McCall, ca. 1989 (Box 1)
    - It Pays to Advertise, by Keith Whitley, Telegraph Magazine, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Ogilvy & Mather's Design for Multinational Marketing, Marketing/Communications, 1970 Sept. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1960-1980 (See also Oversize Materials, Oversize Box OV3.), (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Letters of congratulations, 1958 (Box 1)
    - To and from David Ogilvy, 1961-1986 (Box 1)
  - Dinner in tribute to David Ogilvy, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Memoir of David McCall's tenure at Ogilvy & Mather, undated (Box 1)
  - Printed material, Viewpoint, 1990 Mar.-Apr. (Box 1)
  - Reports
    - 35th Annual Staff Meeting, 1983 (Box 1)
    - An Investigation into the Effects of Comparative Print Advertising that Names Competitive Brands, by O&M Research, ca. 1974 (Box 1)
    - The Unpublished David Ogilvy, 1986 (Box 1)
- McCaffrey & McCall Series (Includes C.J. Laroche & Co.), 1958-1992 and undated, (7 boxes)
  Includes correspondence, corporate publications and client files. Legal documents that detail McCall's initial investment and employment in the C.J. Laroche & Co. agency, which was eventually renamed McCaffrey & McCall, are included. Major clients include Mercedes-Benz of North America, the New York Zoological Society and Save the Children. McCall also worked on the mayoral (New York, N.Y.) campaign of John Lindsay. The series is arranged into four subseries--Administrative Files, Clients, Correspondence and Memoranda, and Printed Materials--and alphabetically therein.
  - Administrative Files Subseries, 1962-1989 and undated
    - Corporate identity proposals and notes, undated (Box 2)
    - Direct marketing, 1981-1985 (Box 2)
    - Entertainment Division, 1987 (Box 2)
    - Executive biographies, undated (Box 2)
    - Expenses, 1973-1988 (Box 2)
    - Financial matters, 1984-1988 (Box 2)
    - How the McCaffrey & McCall Fee Works, undated (Box 2)
    - Legal matters, 1971-1989 (Box 2)
    - Loan agreement between McCall and C.J. LaRoche & Co., 1962 (Box 2)
    - Manning, Michael J. (Jim), 1978-1987 (Box 2)
      Manning was an executive at McCaffrey & McCall.
    - McCaffrey (Jim) retirement announcement, 1973 (Box 2)
    - McCall's employment contract with C.J. LaRoche & Co., 1962 (Box 2)
    - Mission statement, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - Newall & Yohe, Inc., 1978 (Box 2)
      Consultants on Schoolhouse Rock!
    - News releases, 1980-1987 (Box 2)
    - Office procedures, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Payroll summaries, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
    - Personnel recommendations, 1981-1989, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Photographs of staff, undated, (4 folders) (Box 2)
    - Plan for the Agency, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Public relations, 1979-1986 (See also Oversize Materials, Oversize Box OV3.) (Box 2)
    - Reorganization, 1987 (Box 2)
    - Solicitations, 1974-1987, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Status of present accounts, 1987 Feb. 23 (Box 3)
    - Stockholders agreement between McCaffrey, McCall, and C.J. LaRoche & Co., 1962 (Box 3)
    - U.S. Open tennis tournament (corporate tickets), 1986-1988 (Box 3)
    - Wall Street Journal conference, group photograph, 1987 (Box 3)
  - Clients Subseries, 1964-1992 and undated
    - Commercial (See also Oversize Materials, Oversize Box OV3 and Oversize Folder 1.) (Box 3)
      - List of recently produced commercials, 1983 (Box 3)
      - Mercedes-Benz of North America, 1979-1988 (See also Oversize Materials, Oversize Box OV3.)
        - Advertising copy, 1979-1981, (2 folders) (Box 3)
        - Bruce McCall files, 1979-1987 (Box 3)
          No relation to David McCall. Bruce worked as Creative Director of the Mercedes account.
        - Business plan, 1982 (Box 3)
        - Clippings, 1982 and undated (Box 3)
        - Correspondence
          - General, 1981-1988 (Box 3)
          - Letters of congratulations, 1979 (Box 3)
            Concerns McCaffrey & McCall winning the Mercedes account.
        - Meetings, 1979-1980 (Box 3)
        - Mercedes-Benz staffing and organizational charts, 1979-1982 (Box 3)
        - Publication, Mercedes, 1982-1983 (Box 3)
        - Radio advertising, 1986 (Box 3)
        - Report, An Evaluation of Mercedes-Benz Advertising, undated (Box 3)
        - Reports and presentations, 1979-1984 (Box 3)
        - Research, 1982-1985 (Box 3)
        - Sporting events sponsorship, 1982-1987 (Box 3)
        - Travel (Box 4)
          - Inge Bausch to New York, 1987 (Box 4)
          - To Germany, 1979 (Box 4)
          - To Germany - photographs, 1987 (Box 4)
      - National Geographic, Proofs, 1982 (Box 4)
      - Trips: The Travel Advantage, slide presentation, undated (Box 4)
        Trips was a travel planning company.
      - Video Visions Associates, 1985, (2 folders) (See also Oversize Materials, Oversize Box OV3.) (Box 4)
    - House/Agency Advertisements
      - Call McCall
        - Version A, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
        - Version B, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
        - Version C, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
        - Print brochure, 1981 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, 1979-1981 (Box 4)
      - Hard Part is Making It Simple, undated (Box 4)
      - Jim Manning retirement, 1978 (See also Oversize Materials, Oversize Box OV3.) (Box 4)
      - J.C. Penney, congratulatory letters, 1983-1984 (See also Oversize Materials, Oversize Box OV3.) (Box 4)
        Concerning Thank You house advertisement McCall ran after losing the Penney's account.
    - New Business (See also Oversize Materials, Oversize Box OV3.)
      - About McCaffrey & McCall, ca. 1974 (Box 4)
      - Agency mission/philosophy, 1986 (Box 4)
      - Background on McCaffrey & McCall for prospective clients, ca. 1973 (Box 4)
      - Bahamas Ministry of Tourism, 1977 (Box 4)
      - CBS, Inc., 1987 (Box 4)
      - Citibank presentation, undated (Box 4)
      - Correspondence with prospective clients (by product category)
        - Apparel, 1976-1981 (Box 4)
        - Automotive, 1976-1983 (Box 4)
        - Banking and finance, 1976-1983 (Box 4)
        - Camera equipment, 1980-1981 (Box 4)
        - Food and beverage, 1971-1981 (Box 4)
        - General, 1974-1982 (Box 4)
        - Institutional, 1977-1982 (Box 4)
        - Manufacturing, 1975-1983 (Box 4)
        - Personal products, 1976-1981 (Box 4)
        - Publishing, 1976-1981 (Box 4)
        - Utilities, 1977-1982 (Box 4)
      - Epstein (drug store catalogue), 1988 (Box 4)
      - Exxon Company, USA, 1985 (Box 4)
      - Fiat Motors of North America, Inc., 1978 (Box 5)
      - Fortune Systems Corporation, 1982 (Box 5)
      - IBM (Sam Hartwell), 1988 (Box 5)
      - Introduction forms, 1985 (Box 5)
      - J.C. Penney Company, 1987-1988 (Box 5)
      - Lists of businesses in New York, N.Y., located near McCaffrey & McCall offices, undated (Box 5)
      - Mego Corporation, 1976 (Box 5)
      - New England Consulting Service, 1983 (Box 5)
      - North American Philips Lighting Corporation (NAPLC), 1982-1983 (Box 5)
      - Pennzoil Company, 1985-1987 (Box 5)
      - Philips International, 1985 (Box 5)
      - RCA, 1987 (Box 5)
      - Reports, 1981-1983 (Box 5)
      - Snowbird (B. Johnson), 1987 (Box 5)
    - Political (See also Oversize Materials, Oversize Box OV3.)
      - John Lindsay
        Mayor of New York, N.Y., 1966-1973.
        - Correspondence, 1964-1967 (Box 5)
        - Re-election campaign, 1968-1969, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Pro Bono, Public Service and Nonprofit
      - American Association of Retired Persons (AARP), ca. 1988 (See also Oversize Materials, Oversize Box OV1.) (Box 5)
      - Campfire Club of America, 1969 (Box 5)
      - Committee for the Support of Roe v. Wade, 1991 (See also Oversize Materials, Oversize Box OV3.) (Box 5)
      - New York Urban League, undated (See also Oversize Materials, Oversize Box OV3) (Box 5)
      - New York Zoological Society
        - Annual Reports, 1978, 1982-1983, 1985-1986 (Box 5)
        - Brochures and member passes, 1978, 1980 and undated (Box 5)
        - Correspondence and memoranda, 1981-1984 (Box 5)